Guide to the Chinese American Citizens Alliance (Houston Chapter) records, 1953-2015 MS 606
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Chinese American Citizens Alliance (Houston Chapter) records
1953-2015
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Chen, E. C. M. (Edward C. M.); Wu, Linda
MS 606
5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
This collection contains correspondence, programs, and other papers regarding or created by the Chinese American Citizens Alliance (CACA), related to the national organization or to the Houston Lodge specifically, as well as personal papers of Edward K.T. Chen. It also contains a variety of materials about Asian-Americans and Chinese-Americans. (3 boxes)
Historical Note
The Chinese American Citizens Alliance is an organization created in 1895 in San Francisco, California by a group of Chinese Americans who wished to celebrate their heritage and fight against the prejudice they were facing at the time. The Alliance's purpose was to provide support for the Chinese American community, as well as other Asian American groups, by linking the traditions and culture of their homeland with the ideals and customs of America. They also fought to represent the rights of Chinese Americans and were instrumental in improving the legal status of Chinese Americans and other Asian Americans across the country.
The Alliance's first name, "Native Sons of the Golden State," was replaced in 1915 for the "Chinese American Citizens Alliance" due to increased national interest. The San Francisco site became the Grand Lodge and acts as the governing body of the Alliance, with 18 existing Lodges across the country.
The Houston Lodge was established in 1954 with Edward K.T. Chen as the founding President. Along with providing a close relationship with the Chinese American community of Houston, the Houston Lodge has presented the Miss Chinatown Houston Scholarship Pageant every year since 1971.
Scope and Contents
The Chinese American Citizens Alliance records contain documents and artifacts relating to the CACA, at the national and Houston levels, as well as personal papers of Edward K.T. Chen and other various papers on Asian and Chinese Americans.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Accruals
Additional materials may be acquired for this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Dr. Edward C.M. Chen on September 26, 2012 and Mrs. Linda Wu in November, 2015, and Mrs. Judy Lee, in 2021.
Related Materials
Houston Asian American Archives oral history interviews, 1980-2015, MS 573 http://library.rice.edu/collections/WRC/finding-aids/manuscripts/0573">http://library.rice.edu/collections/WRC/finding-aids/manuscripts/0573
Edward C.M. Chen Family Collection, MS 561 http://library.rice.edu/collections/WRC/finding-aids/manuscripts/0561">http://library.rice.edu/collections/WRC/finding-aids/manuscripts/0561
Index Terms
Subjects
Social life and customs; Emigration and immigration; Chinese Americans; Asian Americans; Business; Women
Document Types
letters (correspondence); directories; programs (documents); awards; photographs; posters
Places
Texas--Houston
Subjects (Persons)
Chen, Edward Kin Tung; Wu, Linda
Subjects (Corporations)
Chinese American Citizens Alliance
- Series I: Chinese American Citizens Alliance, 1954-2002; 179446
  General
  This series contains items related to the CACA on a national level.
  - National Convention Programs, 1955-1973, 1985; 179449 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Also includes Proceedings for 1967.
  - National Convention Programs, 1975-1993; 179450 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - National Correspondence, 1954-1973; 179451 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - National records including constitution, by-laws, ceremonies, 1961-1963, n.d.; 179452 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - National Publications, 1970-1975; 179453 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - San Francisco Convention Program, 1987; 179454 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Asian/Pacific Heritage Parade Participants Award, 2002; 179499 (Box 1)
- Series II: Chinese American Citizens Alliance, Houston Lodge, 1953-2015; 179447
  This series contains materials relating specifically to the Houston Lodge, including information on members and related functions, and information about the Houston Asian community.
  - Houston Lodge Correspondence, 1980-1984; 179455 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Houston Lodge records, including directories, rosters, constitution, by-laws, building project, 1954-2015, n.d.; 179456 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Houston Lodge Publications, 1953-1974; 179457 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Edward K.T. Chen Papers, 1996-2009, n.d.; 179458 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - D.A. Bronstein Paper, abstract and pages 1-100, 179459 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Material off of CD-ROM
  - D.A. Bronstein Paper, pages 101-248, n.d.; 179460 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hard Copy Files from CD-ROM, 2008 and n.d.; 179461 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Madame Chiang Kai-Shek Information, n.d.; 179462 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - C.A.C.A. Houston Lodge photos of special events, 1958-1999 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Images of C.A.C.A. Houston Lodge officers, leaders and members at official events and social occasions. Albert and Jane Gee, Women's Auxilliary, Grand Lodge Presdient Francis Louie, Grand Lodge Presdient Wilbur Woo. Also includes special guests Miss Chinatown USA, Connie Chung, Miss China, Miss Texas, and others.
  - C.A.C.A. Houston Lodge programs for Millennium Gala (2000 and 2002) and Youth Club Friends Reunion (1995) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Houston Lodge Anniversary Programs, 1956-1972; 179463 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Houston Lodge Anniversary Programs, 1974-1979; 179464 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Houston Lodge Anniversary Programs, 1982-1992; 179465 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Houston Lodge Anniversary Programs, 1994-2014; 179466 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Houston Lodge Women's Auxiliary, 1962-1977; 179467 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Houston Lodge Members, 1958 and n.d.; 179468 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Houston Lodge Members, 1960-1977; 179469 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miss Chinatown Pageant Correspondence, 1955; 179470 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Miss Chinatown Pageant Programs, 1971-1984; 179471 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Specific program event dates include: 1971, 1972, 1973, 1974, 1975, 1976, 1980, 1981, 1982, 1983, 1984
  - Miss Chinatown Pageant Programs, 1985-1989; 179472 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Specific program event dates include: 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988, 1989
  - Miss Chinatown Pageant Programs, 1991-1996; 179473 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Specific program event dates include: 1990, 1991, 1992, 1993, 1994, 1996
  - Miss Chinatown Pageant Programs, 1997-2003; 179474 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Specific program event dates include: 1997, 1998, 1999, 2000, 2001, 2002, 2003
  - Miss Chinatown Pageant Programs, 2005-2006; 179475 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Specific program event dates include: 2005, 2006, plus Houston Southwest Chinatown Guide featuring Miss Chinatown winners 2004-2006.
  - Miss Chinatown Pageant Programs, 2007-2016; 179476 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Specific program event dates include: 2007, 2008, 2009, 2010, 2011, 2012, 2014, 2015. Also includes Miss Chinatown USA pageant program for 2015, and printed slideshows of Miss Chinatown Houston images 1971-2009.
  - Chinese-American Directory of Greater Houston, 1959-1960; 179477 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Houston Chinese American Telephone Directories, 1967-1969; 179478 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Series III: Asian American and Chinese American associations, 1977-2001; 179448
  This series contains information on various Asian American and Chinese American associations and topics.
  - The Association of Chinese Organizations of Houston Texas, 1997-1998, 2000; 179479 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Chinese Booklets, n.d.; 179480 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Items written in Chinese only.
  - Chinese Culture in the United States of America, 1977; 179482 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Committee of 100 Survey, 2001; 179483 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Houston-Taipei Society, Inc. By-laws, 1997; 179484 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Houston Young Chinese-American Council, 1989; 179485 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Texas Asian Republican Caucus, 1997; 179486 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Asian American Heritage Association: Sharing Our Heritage (VHS) 2 Copies and DVD copy, 179496 (Box 1)
  - Becoming American: The Chinese Experience (CD-ROM), n.d.; 179497 (Box 1)
  - How To Speak Chinese Records, n.d.; 179494 (Box 1)
- Series IV: Oversize Materials, 1965-2016; 179487
  This series contains oversize materials from all other series.
  - Chinese American Outlook Newsletter, 1985; 179488 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - United States, State of Texas, Harris County resolutions honoring C.A.C.A Houston Lodge's 50th anniversary, 2004; 179489 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Hermann Park Chinese Pavilion Monument Plans, n.d.; 179490 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Houston Lodge Proclamation, 1984; 179491 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Houston Young Chinese-American Council, 1989; 179492 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miss Chinatown Pageant Proclamation, 1993; 179493 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Certificate of Merit presented to Edward C.M. Chen from the Chinese American Citizens Alliance Grand Lodge, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Certificate of Merit presented to Jane E. Gee from the Chinese American Citizens Alliance Grand Lodge, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    First certificate of merit awarded to a woman by C.A.C.A. Template includes wording describing "his" meritorious service since there had been no female recipients previously.
  - Certificate of Merit presented to Albert Gee from the Chinese American Citizens Alliance Grand Lodge, 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - C.A.C.A. National Convention, 1977, group photos with names written in (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - C.A.C.A. Youth Club Balls scrapbook of programs, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - C.A.C.A. Houston Lodge photo scrapbook of activities, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - C.A.C.A. Houston Lodge Youth Club photo scrapbook of activities, featuring Ed. C.M. Chen, Harry Gee, Jr., Carol Anne Gee, Mylew Joe, Ann Wong, Katy Lee, Linda Gee, Molly Gee, Ron Chow, Ted Wu, Richard Eng, Kristin Wu, and others, 1958-1999 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - C.A.C.A. Houston bowling trophies, 1965 (3) (Map-drawer Annex)
    Collection of trophies won by the Houston Lodge CACA, as well as the Women's Auxiliary Houston Lodge CACA.
  - Miss Chinatown pageant posters featuring contestants and sponsors, 2004-2016 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Miss Chinatown newsclippings, 1976-2010 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Miss Chinatown as featured in Yellow magazine, 2007-2009 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Miss Chinatown pageant poster, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - CACA Grand Lodge Merit Award: Plaque from the CACA Grand Lodge awarded to the Houston Lodge for the "A Salute to Education" community project, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - CACA Grand Lodge Plaque from the CACA Grand Lodge awarded to the Houston Lodge recognizing its contribution and service to the CACA., 1974 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Houston Lodge Presidents' Plaque presented to the previous CACA presidents for their dedication to the Houston Lodge, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Grand Lodge Award of Recognition presented to Edward R. T. Chen for "Outstanding Leadership and Accomplishment as President, Houston Lodge", 1955 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Houston Lodge award honoring Dr. and Mrs. Edward C. M. Chen for the establishment of the Chen Miss Chinatown Houston Scholarship Fund, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - National C.A.C.A congratulations to Houston Lodge on 50th anniversary, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - C.A.C.A. Asian Pacific Heritage Parade Participants recognition, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Award presented by Chinese Classical Dance Group, National Taiwan Academy of Arts, The Republic of China, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Gavel with engraved plate "Edward K.T. Chen, President, Houston Lodge, Chinese American Citizens Alliance, 1954-55-56" (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - CACA group with Miss Chinatown, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Series V: Addendum of Directories and Programs
  - C.A.C.A. Youth Club event programs, 1970-1995 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - C.A.C.A. Women's Auxiliary to the Houston Lodge yearbooks, 1963-1979 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Chinese Professional Club directories, 1978-2008 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Chinese Professional Association Scholarship Ball programs, 1989-2008 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - CACA Telephone Directory and Business Calendar, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - CACA Youth Club Constitution with 1971 amendments (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Chinese Baptist Church Favorite Recipes, Book 2 (Houston, TX), 1976 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Chinese Baptist Church Directory (Houston, TX), 1965 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Houston Chinese Directory, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Celebrating the Founding of the Guangdong Association of Texas (program booklet), 2003 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - "Say It In Chinese" by T. Y. Wu, Institute of Chinese Culture, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Houston Chinese Telephone Book, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Asian Chamber of Commerce Directory (Houston, TX), 2005 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Houston Chinese Catholic Directory, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Bridge of Heritage: The Institute of Chinese Culture 30th Anniversary Special Edition (booklet, Houston, TX), 2000 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Chinese American Legion Post 596 certificates, 1970s (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - 14th Air Service Group and 987th Signal Company, 2001 Combined Reunion, Houston, TX (booklet) (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - CACA National convention programs, 1999, 2001, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Resolution To Seek a Congressional Apology, Submitted by the Chinese American Citizens Alliance, Greater San Gabriel Valley Lodge, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - CACA gala programs, New York and Boston, 2016-2018 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Highlights of Interim Report to the President, White House Initiative on Asian American and Pacific Islanders, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - CACA 2017 Spirit of America Awards judging panel program (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Chinese Community Center Houston, gala program, 2005-2015 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Organization of Chinese Americans Greater Houston Chapter 25th Anniversary "They Serve with Honor" awards banquet program, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - National Day Celebration of the People's Republic of China, gala programs, Houston, 1998, 2003, 2016 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Asian Pacific American Organizations directories, 1999-200, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 32)
- Series VI: Congressional Gold Medal Honoring Chinese American Veterans of World War II
  - Congressional Gold Medal Honoring Chinese American Veterans of World War II event program 2020, with Public Law 115-337, 115th Congress, 2018 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Congressional Gold Medal Honoring Chinese American Veterans of World War II, event name tag, Ed Gor, representing Chinese American Citizens Alliance (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Congressional Gold Medal Honoring Chinese American Veterans of World War II, award medal housed in original United States Mint box (Box 7, Envelope 2)